译者｜佚名　　校润｜小众电影@电灯泡
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
打败了法国
Victory over France!
西线投降了
West front surrenders!
打败了法国
Victory over France!
法国人被打败了
The French are defeated!
- 早上好 弗洛姆法官  - 你好
- Good morning, judge Fromm  - Yeah!
今天没你的信
There's nothing for you today
在我看来这是好消息
That is what I call good news
我祝你有个愉快的一天
I wish you a nice day just the same
法官大人
Your honor
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler!
什么消息
So what's the news?
一封军方邮局寄来的信 打印的
A letter from the military postal service. Typed
谁死了
Who?
昆格尔的儿子
Quangel's son
昆格尔先生 你的信
Herr Quangel, for you
儿子出事了？
Something has happened to the boy?
这些骗子
Those liars!
安娜
Anna
这要怪你 你和你该死的战争
You're to blame You and your damn war!
你和你该死的元首
You and your damn fuhrer!
- 安娜  - 拜托
- Anna  - Please.
让我静静
Leave me alone
是我 爱娃
It's me, Eva
罗森塔尔夫人？
Frau Rosenthal?
有我丈夫的信吗
Anything from my husband?
谢谢你 爱娃
Thank you, Eva
你需要什么
What do you need?
我需要的不多
I don't need much
和平时一样
As always
柏林孤影
贡比涅停战协定签署
标志一战以同盟国的失败而告终
早上好
Morning
你也 [意大利语]
昆格尔夫人 你需要多少黄油
Frau Quangel, how much butter do you need?
半磅？和平时一样？
Half a pound? Your usual?
你有了牛奶和鸡蛋
You have milk and eggs
- 还需要多少黄油？ - 我…
- Now how much butter do you need?  - I.
拜托
Oh, come on!
- 过来  - 快点
- Come along  - Hurry up
昆格尔夫人 我送你回家
Frau Quangel? I'll take you home
汉斯·昆格尔
1940年1月23日
元首
骗子
我下班后就直接回家
I'll be straight home from work
嗨 昆格尔先生 怎么这么急
Hey, Quangel What's the hurry?
出什么事了吗
Is something wrong?
我们要发财了
We're going to get rich
战胜了法国
A victory over France
知道这意味着什么吗
Know what that means?
我们将成为世上最富裕的国家
We're gonna be the richest country in the whole world!
再过几周我们就能
So, in the next few weeks we will have
摧毁英国 结束战争
destroyed England and ended the war
既然前线的部队
And since the troops on the front
一直高奏凯歌
have been so victorious
我们在后方的人也要尽到自己的责任
it's time that those of us at home do our duty as well
元首希望增加产量
The fuhrer wants to increase production
他希望产量在三个月内
He expects productivity to rise by 30 percent
增加三成 再过半年
in three months and to double that
再增加三成
within the next half a year
元首的希望就是我们的命令
The fuhrer's wish is our command
我们现在征求建议
We will now receive any proposals
如何实现这一目标
about how to reach this goal
- 胜利  - 胜利
- Sieg Heil!  - Sieg Heil!
工人们 谁有话要说吗
Workers, does anyone have anything to say?
好的 昆格尔工头
Yes, foreman Quangel?
要提高产量 必须安置
To increase productivity, additional machines
更多的机器 还要解雇一些开小差的
must be installed and a few shirkers laid off
你什么意思
What are you talking about?
这些开小差的是谁
Who are those shirkers?
一部分是跟不上工作节奏的
Some can't keep up with the work pace
另一部分根本不想跟上
Others don't want to
高谈政治却逃避工作
Talking politics, skipping work
这里有些人对此很擅长
Some men here are good at it Very good
你怎么能这么说 昆格尔
How dare you talk like that, Quangel?
你没有入党
You're not in the party!
你怎么敢污蔑党员
How dare you discredit members of the party!
昆格尔只考虑自己
Quangel only thinks of himself
你有没有为冬季救济金和元首
Do you donate anything to the winter relief fund?
捐赠过什么吗
And to the fuhrer?
国家带走了我的独子
Germany has taken my only son
昨天我接到通知他阵亡了
Yesterday, I was informed he died in combat
为了你们 为了元首
For you. For the fuhrer
我来问你 多尔法斯
I ask you, Dolfuss
还有比捐献自己儿子
What more can a man donate
捐的更多的吗
than his child?
安娜 我们还要去征召劳工
Anna! Anna, we have visits to make!
纳粹妇联在等着你
The Nazi women's league is waiting for you!
希特勒万岁 安娜 你去哪儿了
Heil Hitler, Anna! Where were you?
- 我们迟到了  - 快点
- We're late!  - Now, come on
该走了
It's time to go
- 我们去楼下等你  - 我换衣服 我换衣服
- We'll wait downstairs  - I'll change. I'll change
先是格尔达·克兰施密特夫人
So, first that Frau Gerda Kleinschmidt
然后是一位威尼克夫人
Then there's a Frau else Wernicke
就住在附近 然后是…
who just lives around the corner, and then.
你们听着 克莱尔·格里奇
Ah, listen to this, Claire Gehrich
她是格里奇中校的老婆
Ah, she's the wife of Obersturmbannfuhrer Gehrich
找她的话 需要说的很委婉
You have to be really diplomatic if you visit her
- 要不要把她划掉  - 不 我们不能这么做
- Should I cross her out?  - No, no, we can't do that
我们要尽到责任
We all have to do our part
但今天就不去找她了
but, uh, perhaps not today
找她那样的人需要有良好的体格
We have to be in good shape for someone like that
多么好的房子
What a nice place
有什么事吗
What can I do for you?
你的丈夫
Your husband?
是的
Yes
你丈夫正在波兰作战
Your husband's fighting in Poland
是不是 克兰施密特夫人
isn't he, Frau Kleinschmidt?
他每天都为他的民族和祖国
He's risking his life, day after day for his people
冒生命危险 而你却在柏林寻欢作乐
and his fatherland while you are having a good time in Berlin
你不羞愧吗
Aren't you ashamed?
可我…
But I.
可是…
But.
没人理解
Nobody understands
我很担心他
I'm so worried for him
我很担心 可是
I'm so worried, but.
都走开
Knock it off!
接着干活
Get back to work
别以为这样就不会召你入伍了
Don't think this will save you from the front
我不想撒谎
I'm not going to lie
我知道你是故意自残
I know you did it on purpose
知道吗
You understand?
如果门铃响了 不要开门
If the doorbell rings, don't open the door
谁来都不开门
For anyone
- 奥托  - 我在写字
- Otto?  - I'm writing
写给谁
To who?
我不知道
I don't know
我在写卡片
I'm writing cards
讲述真相的卡片
Cards that tell the truth
人们会看到这些卡片
People will read these cards
会相互传阅
They will pass them on
卡片？
Cards?
你在写卡片？
You're scribbling cards?
这有什么用处
What is that supposed to do?
母亲：元首害死了我儿子
母亲：他甚至害死了你(此明信片请勿流通)
你为什么写这种字体
Why are you writing like that?
我是掩盖我的笔迹
I'm disguising my handwriting
让我来吧 拜托
Let me do it. Please
都没上锁
It isn't even locked
如果她喊叫怎么办
What if she screams?
她不会喊叫的
She won't scream
我的笨老婆还给她送饭
My stupid wife takes food to her
那个老犹太人
The old Jew
她的店被人烧了之后 她把东西都拉到这里来了
She hauled all her stuff up here after they burned her shop
她在躲藏
She's hiding
安静
Calm down
爸爸 楼上
Papa, upstairs
我们走 快
Let's go. Quickly
你来这里干什么
What are you doing here?
巴克豪森 你来这房子干什么
Barkhausen, what are you doing in this apartment?
帕西卡先生
Herr Persicke.
邻居 我们可以分享
Neighbor, we can share
是罗森塔尔夫人
It's Frau Rosenthal
- 拜托 这不是我的错  - 出去
- Please, it's not my fault  - Out
找钱
Look for the money
我很抱歉
I'm sorry
没必要抱歉
There's no need to be
你可以住在我们这里
You can stay with us
这对你太危险了
This is too dangerous for you
- 嘘  - 弗洛姆法官
- Ssh.  - Judge Fromm?
跟我来夫人 快
Come with me, madame Quickly
他们还会来的
They'll be back
嘘 安静 进去
Ssh, be quiet. Come in
我已故女儿的房间
My deceased daughter's room
没人会来这里找你
No one will look for you here
尽量适应一下这里
Try to get used to it
去睡觉到明早
Go to sleep and tomorrow morning
你要一切按我说的做
you will listen exactly to what I say
明天
Tomorrow
晚安 罗森塔尔夫人
Goodnight, Frau Rosenthal
她回她的家了吗
Is she back in her apartment?
- 不行  - 我跟你一起去
- No  - I'm coming with you
你休想拦住我
You can't stop me
他们会绞死你的 他们也会绞死女人
They'll hang you They hang women, too
他们当然会
Of course they do
你只去办公楼前
You only go up to the building
我进去放置卡片
I go inside. I place the card
我很快回来
I'll be right back
我等会就接待你
I'll be with you in a minute
这里来先生
This way, sir
八十芬尼
80 pfennig, please
- 一杯杜松子酒  - 我要一杯咖啡
- A schnapps  - Coffee for me
不了 我也要一杯杜松子酒
No, I'll have a schnapps, too
那么我们开始了
So, we begin
从今以后我们就孤军作战了
From now on we are alone
在一段时间内
You will not leave this room
你不能离开这房间
for a certain period of time
可能要很长时间 你是我的客人
Possibly a long time, you are my guest
但相信我
But believe me
只要你一走出这个门
the moment you step out of that door
我就不认识你了
I will no longer know you
你知道我在法院的绰号吧
You know what they called me in the courtroom, don't you?
不知道？冷血弗洛姆
No? Cold-blooded Fromm
我听命于一个女主人
I have a mistress whom I obey
她的名字叫正义
Her name is justice
可我希望我丈夫回家时
But I want to be in the apartment
我能在家里等着
when my husband arrives
你清楚他是不会回来的 罗森塔尔夫人
He isn't coming back and you know that, Frau Rosenthal
锁上门好吗
Lock the door. Yes?
巴克豪森在哪儿 他住在哪儿
Where is this Barkhausen, then? Where does he live?
就是这里
It's right here
你听说过那个失踪的老太太吗
Have you heard of that old woman that disappeared?
我知道她
I know her
去看看他们要干什么去
See what they want. Go on!
喂 老头在家吗
Hey, is the old man at home?
这跟你有啥关系
What's it got to do with you?
关系很大
A lot
跟警方关系也很大
It's got a lot to do with the police, too
也跟党员有关
and with the man at the party
就是他 督查 他和另一个流氓
That's him, inspector It was him and the other bum
那个女邮递员的丈夫
The husband of the postmistress
我和我父亲
My father and me, we caught them in that
发现他们在那犹太女人的家中
Jewish woman's apartment on the fifth floor
他们想把东西都搬出去
They wanted to clear everything out
你应该予以没收
You ought to have it confiscated
你们也这么干的
You did it yourself, you creep
- 你和你父亲  - 我们走
- You and your father  - Let's go
我们去跟他那女人谈谈
Let's talk to the woman
她不在楼上
She isn't upstairs
弗洛姆先生
Herr Fromm...
你要称呼我法官大人
for you I'm still, your honor
你的上级是谁
Who is your commanding officer?
埃舍里希 埃舍里希督查
Escherich Inspector Escherich
阿布雷希普林茨大街警察局
Police headquarters Prinz Albrecht Strasse
我知道地址
I know the address
让他过来
Get him here
然后你离开我的家
And then you leave this apartment
我可不会
Like hell I will
你自己住在这里？
So, you live alone?
你不介意我搜查一下吧
You don't mind if I look around, do you?
再见
Good day
你没看到
You should have seen it
我爸发现了他们 他们很害怕
Papa got into them, he had them scared
然后我和我哥去追
Then me and my brother went after him
他俩狼狈逃走
and his buddy and really had them running
巴尔德尔？
Baldur?
我哥哥是党卫军少校
My brother's an ss Sturmbannfuhrer
是你吗 巴尔德尔·帕西卡？
Is that you? Baldur Persicke?
你以前经常来我家玩
You often played in my apartment
你按门铃
You'd ring the bell
因为我给你苹果蛋糕吃
because I gave you apple cake
对吗
Right?
你现在长这么高了
How big you are now
还这么壮实
And how strong
带她出去
Get her out
- 可是…  - 只管去吧
- But...  - Just go!
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler!
不
No!
她死了 奥托
She's dead, Otto
我看到了
I saw
你说过你看到弗洛姆法官把那老女人
You said you saw how judge Fromm hid the old woman
藏在家里是不是
at his place, didn't you?
你知道你闯出了什么祸
You know what's going on in this apartment house
闯入私宅
A break-in, unlawful appropriation
浪费警力
of national wealth
诬告一名无辜公民
a denunciation of a respectable citizen
这就够了
Enough!
我只是…
Oh, I just.
而且还害死了一个女人
And a dead woman who was very much alive a moment ago
这次你的罪大了
You're not getting out of this one
你不能这么做你不能
You can't do this No, you can't
他可以这么做 但他不会
Oh, yes, he can, but he won't
因为他是个警督 不是恶人
Because he's a police counsellor and not a monster
我相信这位先生没拿走
I'm sure this gentleman didn't take
任何不属于他的东西
anything that doesn't belong to him
因为他清楚这样会意味着什么
because he knows exactly what that would mean
因此他离开这里之后
So, he will do what he does best
会做他所擅长的
when he leaves this place
他会回到他的公寓
He will return to his comfortable little apartment
监视附近的一举一动
And he will observe what is going on here
我当然会的 督查
Yes, of course, inspector I will
你可以走了
You can leave now
法官大人 出什么事了吗
Your honor, did something happen?
罗森塔尔夫人 有没有…
I mean, has Frau Rosenthal been...
我不懂你在说什么 克鲁格夫人
I don't know what you are talking about, Frau kluge
失陪了
Now, if you'll please excuse me
我要这五张明信片
I'll take these five cards, please
- 要邮票吗  - 不 我已经有邮票了
- With stamps?  - No, I, I already have stamps
谢谢
Thank you
总共二十五芬尼
That makes 25 pfennig
我为你包起来
I'll wrap it up for you right away
我需要手套 薄手套
I need gloves. Thin gloves
抱歉 本店不卖手套
Sorry, we don't have any
你可以去…
You might find some.
我想想 也许你可以去…
Let me think Maybe you'll find them...
不用 没关系
no, no, it's fine
这些就够了 谢谢
Just these. Thank you
- 再见  - 再见
- Goodbye  - Goodbye
停止战争机器
你听“希特勒的阴影笼罩欧洲
Listen, "Hitler's shadow falls over Europe
“就像魔鬼的阴影
"like the devil's shadow
传递这张卡片 打倒希特勒政权”
Pass this card on Down with the Hitler regime."
这字真难看 我女儿的字都比这个强
What a scrawl! Even my daughter writes better than that
是吗
Oh, yes?
在我看来 他是个很愚蠢的人
If you ask me, he is an incredibly stupid person
是个来自下层阶级
Someone from the lower classes
靠双手劳动的人
who works with their hands
可能能力不行 但不会愚蠢
Perhaps unskilled, but stupid? No
可能只是个人在发泄
Probably someone just letting off steam
只是一时冲动
Just a flash in the pan
还有别的卡片？
There is more?
母亲 元首害死了我儿子
"Mother The fuhrer murdered my son
母亲 元首也会害死你的孩子们
Mother. The fuhrer will murder your sons, too."
在哪儿
Where?
在国王大街 两周前
Neue Konigstrasse Two weeks ago
也是一个办公大楼里
Another office building
肮脏
Filth
我们怎么办 上报？
So what do we do now? Report it?
要不是警力不足 这本来不算什么
If we had more men, it wouldn't be a problem
我们很快就能抓住这个…该怎么称呼
We would catch this, uh, uh, how shall we call him?
这个淘气鬼
"Hobgoblin," in no time
我会在这两周里
I'd investigate everyone in Berlin
已经调查过柏林所有失去一个儿子的人
who has lost a son within the last two weeks
为什么
Why?
“元首害死了我的儿子”
"The fuhrer murdered my son."
- 只提到一个儿子  - 然后呢
- There's only one son  - And?
我们等待 收集线索
We wait We collect information
加以分析 我们就是吃这碗饭的
Put it together That is our job
我们是德国的专家 不是外行
We're German professionals Not amateurs
如果他继续干下去
What if he goes on doing it
却不再有卡片上交呢
and no more cards are turned in?
谁知道这件事发生多久了
Who knows how long this has been going on
想想在公共场所
Think what it would be like to touch
捡起这种卡片念
one of these cards in a public place
会是什么感觉
To stand there, to read it
知道可能有人正在监视你
Knowing somebody might be watching you
等着记录你的反应
waiting to record your response
这些淘气鬼写的卡片
No, whatever our hobgoblin writes
最后都会送到我们这里来
it's going to end up here with us
我估计能有百分之九十五
Let's say... 95 percent
我觉得不到
I say it's less
敢打赌吗
It's a bet?
那我们等着
So we wait
等待此人露出马脚
We wait for our friend to make a mistake
希特勒不会占上风 正义才有力量
早上好
Good morning
- 请进  - 谢谢
- Please come in  - Thank you
- 希特勒万岁  - 希特勒万岁
- Heil Hitler!  - Heil Hitler!
你是来自纳粹妇联的？我亲爱的夫人
So, you're from the Nazi women's league, my dear Frau?
我让女佣把我的钱包拿来
I'll just have the girl bring me my purse
我不是来募捐的 格里奇夫人
I'm not here for a donation, Frau Gehrich
完全不是
Definitely not
那你到底有什么事
So, what exactly can I do for you?
你为什么没去工作
Why aren't you at work?
你没看到我们的军工厂征召工人吗
Didn't you read our arms industry's calls for help?
看看我
Look at me
看我像是能干体力劳动的人吗
Do I look as if I'm suited to manual labor?
你试过一次吗
Have you ever tried?
我不打算损害我的健康
I'm not about to jeopardize my health
反正我总能搞到一张医疗诊断书
Anyway, I can always get a medical certificate
你当然可以 你可以花二十马克
Of course you can, you can buy one for 20 marks
从私人医生那里买到
from your personal physician
但这次没用了
but that won't help you in this case
这次你需要军工厂的医生开证明
In this case, you need a doctor from a factory
证明你没有工作能力
to certify that you are unable to work
我们指派给你的医生
A doctor that we assign to you
好吧 给我指派个医生 你能看到结果是什么
Alright, sign me a doctor and you'll see what happens
你是在嘲笑我和妇联吗
You're mocking me and the women's league?
嘲笑我们的制度和元首吗
Making fun of our regulations and our fuhrer?
- 我警告你  - 我也警告你
- I warn you  - and I warn you
你看来不知道老娘是谁
You don't seem to know who I am!
我丈夫是中校
My husband is Obersturmbannfuhrer!
这就更严重了 中校夫人
That makes it even worse, Frau Obersturmbannfuhrer
我们还会联系你的
You'll hear from us
除非你还有别的重要信息
Unless you have any more significant information?
比如有个生病的母亲
An ill mother, perhaps?
你的身份证和你的姓名马上交出来
Your ID and your name At once!
我保证你不会有好果子吃
I promise you, there will be consequences
拿去
Here you are
我没有名片
I don't have any calling cards.
因为我只是个普通工人
Because I'm just a common worker
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler
不 我不明白
No, I don't understand
那女人在劳务责任法的管辖范围内
That woman comes under the labor service duty law
这一点你很清楚
And you know that as well as I do
格里奇夫人是一位中校的老婆
Frau Gehrich is the wife of an Obersturmbannfuhrer
那么你肯定明白…
So, I'm sure you understand that...
上面哪一条说这种女人
well, where does it say that women like that
可以免除劳动职责
are exempt from general duties?
- 哪一条？ - 别这么顽固
- Where?  - Oh, don't be so obstinate
她需要照顾她劳累工作的丈夫
She has to look after her overworked husband
我也一样
I do, too!
而且我看到那女人有女佣
And from what I saw, that woman has domestic help
我没做错什么
I didn't do anything wrong
我是按我们的规章办事
I acted according to our regulations
那么你会去道歉吗 昆格尔夫人
So, are you going to apologize, Frau Quangel?
为什么道歉
What for?
那我去代你道歉
Then I will do it, on your behalf
另外 你休息一段时间
And you, you take some time off
你们要开除我就因为
Oh, you're throwing me out, because I told
我对那种女人说了实话？
a woman like that the truth?
- 不是  - 不是 你误会我了
- No...  - Oh, no, you misunderstood me
只是休息几天
Just take some time off and rest
恢复你的体力
Gather your strength
这很重要 安娜
That's important, Anna
在刚丧子的这段时间
At a time of mourning
好吗
Alright?
好吧
Alright
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler!
- 希特勒万岁  - 希特勒万岁 昆格尔先生
- Heil Hitler  - Heil Hitler, Herr Quangel
祝你万事如意 安娜
And all the best for you, Anna
谢天谢地
Thank god
- 不需要去妇联了  - 干得好
- No more women's league  - Well done
你怎么这么镇定
How can you be so calm?
我看到手套时差点吓死了
I nearly died when I saw the gloves
手套 安娜 只是手套
Gloves, Anna. Just gloves
我们怎么办 奥托
What are we doing, Otto?
我们失去了儿子 别的人失去了…
We've lost our son Other people have lost.
可他们他们不…
But they, they don't.
这个体制 这个政权…
This system, this regime.
现在我感觉我们自由了
Now I feel that we're free
我是说
I mean.
解脱了 解脱了一切
Freed... From all of it
这就是我的感觉
This is how I feel
邪恶希特勒政府存在一天 就不会有和平
新闻自由 希特勒住手！
相信自己 别被希特勒左右
希特勒 暴力和不公正的代名词
从不带来和平
吕德里茨大街二十三号
Luderitz Strasse 23
- 下一个  - 阿姆斯特丹大街二十七号
- Next  - Amsterdamer Strasse 27
嗨 昆格尔
Hey, Quangel
你们去哪儿 到防空洞里去
Where are you going? Get into the shelter!
这是供母亲和儿童使用的防空洞
It's a shelter for mothers and children, boy
我们进去不合适
So it's not suitable for us
喂 你在这儿干什么 你在干什么
Hey, what are you doing here? What are you doing?
停下
Stop! What.
喂 你停下
Hey, you! Stop!
等等 停下 停下
Wait! Stop! Stop, wait!
等等
Wait!
停下
Stop!
喂
Hey
喂 等等 你是什么人
Hey, you! Wait! Who are you?
你能帮帮我吗
Please, can you help me?
我找不到母亲和儿童用的防空洞了
I need to find the shelter for mothers and children
我迷路了 我女儿正在那里等我
I've lost my way. My daughter is waiting for me there
你肯定熟悉这里的路 拜托了
You must know your way around here. Please
- 你说你女儿？ - 是的
- Your daughter, you say?  - Yeah
- 她多大了  - 她六岁
- How old is she?  - She's only six years old
她说在防空洞里等我
Six. Waiting for me at the shelter, she said
现在她去了防空洞 我却没有
And now she's there and I am not
过两条街就到了
Yeah, in two blocks and you're there
现在安静了 别慌
It's calm now, calm down
那里的人会照顾她的
The people there will take care of her
我不慌 她肯定很害怕哭着
I'm, I'm sure she's frightened and crying.
- 你说两条街？ - 是的
- It's two blocks, you say?  - Yes
两条街后左拐 很好找
Two blocks and then left You can't miss it
- 希特勒万岁  - 希特勒万岁
- Heil Hitler!  - Heil Hitler!
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler!
督查 我看看这个人要干什么
Well, inspector, let's see what your filthy hack is up to
我听说他依然在你眼皮底下
I hear he's still scribbling away
散发卡片
right under your nose, huh?
希特勒万岁 上校
Heil Hitler, Standartenfuhrer
他不肯放弃 不过这也在意料之中
He won't give up It wasn't to be expected anyway
一个人能花一个半小时画这个
Someone who takes one and a half hours to draw that
是很坚定的
is persistent
- 我亲自试过  - 是嘛
- Tried it myself  - Oh, really?
但你放心 我总能查到罪犯
But rest assured, I always find my man
我们的“淘气鬼行动”…
We run our operation hobgoblin...
- 淘气鬼？ - 是的
- Hobgoblin?  - Yes
- 我喜欢这名字  - 那就好
- I like that  - Glad to hear then
根据分布判断 此人住在
Judging by the distribution, the man lives
亚历山大广场附近
somewhere around Alexander square
这里最初没有卡片
There were no cards here at first
但现在他不想走太远
but now he doesn't want to travel so far
在他的居住地区留下了越来越多的卡片
and leaves more and more cards in his own neighborhood
希特勒万岁 上校
Heil Hitler, Standartenfuhrer
有多少
How many?
他也去了东区
He also includes the eastern districts
和商业区这里你看
and downtown. Here, look
我已经问过你 埃舍里希
I asked you a question, Escherich
有多少
How many?
一百二十七张 上校
One hundred and twenty seven, Standartenfuhrer
准确的说是一百二十九张
One hundred and twenty nine, to be exact
今早又有两张
with these two from this morning
- 超过一百张  - 是的
- More than a hundred!  - Yes
既然上交的就超过一百张
If more than a hundred cards were turned in here
你们这些笨蛋有没有想过
doesn't anyone of you wise asses ever think about how much filth
还有多少在外面流传
is still circulating out there?
恕我直言 我们想一想人之常情
With due respect, let's think about human nature
没人会长时间的
No one holds on to these scribblings
留着这些卡片
longer than necessary...
告诉我是谁干的
tell me who's been doing this
因为会有人这么问我
because I will be asked
我需要回答
and I have to answer
现在
Now
英勇的斯大林格勒战役
The heroic battle of Stalingrad
要有人写出真相
Someone has to write the truth
揭穿这些谎言
with all of these lies.
你觉得我们的卡片最后去了哪里
What do you think happens to our cards?
你为何想知道
Why do you want to know?
我想知道别人看了是什么反应
I want to know how people react
有些人大概会害怕
Some people will be afraid, probably
害怕可能有人在监视他们捡起了卡片
Afraid that someone may have watched them pick up the card
有些人可能会把卡片放回去
Some will maybe put them back
有些人会上交
Some people will turn them in
交给警察街道管理员
to policemen, block wardens
但他们也会看到我们的卡片
but our cards will also be read by them
这就像一台机器
It's like with a machine
齿轮中有一点沙子不会让机器停转
A little sand in the gears will not stop the machine.
但如果有个人不停的
But if a person throws a little more sand
往里扔沙子
and, and more.
发动机就开始断断续续的
The motor begins to stutter
流水线就会停下来
the assembly line stops
我在脑海中看到有很多人
In my mind I see lots of people
在向齿轮里扔沙子
throwing sand in the gears
你是个浪漫主义者 奥托·昆格尔
You are a romantic, Otto Quangel
我是个机械工
I'm a mechanic
是的 这也是
Yeah, that, too
你才是浪漫主义者
You are the romantic
至少你以前是
At least, you used to be
什么我以前是？
What? I, I used to be?
毕竟是我先看到你的
Still, I saw you first
你是你先看到我
not the other way around
可你啥也没说
But you didn't say anything
你当时在和彼得·赖因克跳舞
You were dancing with Peter Reinke
然后你跟他去了栗子树下
and then you went with him to the Chestnut tree
你戴着花冠
you with your crown of flowers
笑着好像他多么风趣似的
laughing as if he was incredibly funny
赖因克和他那难看的发型
Reinke with his stupid haircut
他现在是秃子了 也是党员
He's bald now and a member of the party
我本来也会跟你跳舞的
I would have danced with you, too
可你没请我
but you didn't ask
你能看出来我喜欢你
You knew the way I looked at you
总之我两年后请你了
Anyway, I asked you two years later
不是请我跳舞
Not to dance
你想跳舞？
So you'd like a dance?
不 只是…
No, just.
这是他吗 大致上
Is that him, approximately?
是的 差不多
Yes, pretty much. Uh.
他的双眼可能更宽一些 当时天黑
His eyes might be a little bit further apart. It was dark, uh.
谢谢你 为帝国效力了
Thank you. You've done the Reich a great service
希特勒万岁 督查
Heil Hitler, inspector
谢弗小姐
Fraulein Schaefer
把这个发下去
Have this passed around
“传递这个信息加入出版自由
"Pass the information Join the free press
“你已经被恐惧所控制
"Fear has taken control of you
杀了它 杀了希特勒”
Kill it. Kill Hitler."
这是个中老年男子
It's a man who is no longer young
在法国战役中失去了他的独子
who lost his only son in the French campaign
书法不行 但有文化
Inexperienced at writing, but intelligent
在这一年里他的风格发生重大变化
The style has visibly changed during the course of the year
最近几个月 他用了标题“出版自由”
In recent months, he has used the title, "free press."
他的作案方式日渐专业
He's working in an increasingly professional way
从不留下指纹 手段狡猾
He never leaves fingerprints, he operates strategically
不会连续两次选择同一条街
He never chooses the same street twice in a row
他总在七号九号
He always changes between these streetcar lines
十一号电车之间倒车
seven, nine and 11
“每一个反对纳粹的想法
"Each thought against the national socialists
就像罪恶的战争机器里的一粒沙子”
is like sand in the criminal war machine."
“传阅这张卡片出版自由”
"Pass on this card Free press."
“还要死多少孩子”
"How many children have to die?"
“恐惧是他们唯一的武器出版自由”
"Fear is their only weapon Free press."
“帮我们结束这罪恶的战争机器”
"Help us to put an end to the criminal war machine."
佐特 他一次又一次的提到机器
Zott, again and again the picture of a machine
证件
Papers
今天是二十二号
Today is the 22nd
- 今天  - 生日
- Today  - Birthday
有时我能很真切的感受到危险
Sometimes I feel the danger as if it were so physical
- 能感觉到  - 拜托别吓唬我
- I actually feel it  - Please, don't frighten me
不
No
- 为了汉斯  - 汉斯
- To Hans  - Hans
不 埃舍里希督查不在他的办公室里 请等一下
No, inspector Escherich isn't in his office. Just a moment
我是接线员
Operator speaking
洛林大街分局打来的电话
Incoming call from the Lothringer street section
说是逮捕了淘气鬼一案的嫌疑犯
Reported arrest of suspect in the hobgoblin case
好的 我为你接通
Yes, I'll put you through
安娜
Anna
你好 沃尔特
Oh, hello, Walter
- 他私奔了吗 可怜的姑娘  - 不是
- Did he run away? Poor girl  - No
我只是把他的饭盒带来 他又忘在家了
I just brought him his lunch box. He left it again
我还以为他病了 他没来上班
Oh, I thought he was ill He isn't here
安娜 你好吗 你真好看
Anna, how are you doing? You look great
我快要结婚了
I'm getting married soon!
- 绞死他太便宜他了  - 叛徒
- Hanging's too good for you!  - Traitor!
你是个叛徒 你是人民的敌人
You're a traitor! You're an enemy to the people!
- 噢  - 你在这儿干什么
- Oh!  - What are you doing here?
等等 我们说过我们一起干的
Oh, wait We said we'd do this together
- 你怎么没去工作  - 现在不方便
- Why didn't you go to work?  - Not now
叛徒
Traitor!
你知道我今天是什么心情吗
Do you know what my day was like?
你没考虑过吧
No. You don't think of that, do you?
发现你不在工厂
Finding you're not at work
然后想到你还在大楼里面
and then thinking you're still inside that building
你知道我是什么心情吗
You know what that's like for me?
怎么了奥托 你想被抓住吗
What is it, Otto? You want to get caught?
是这样吗
Is that what it is?
- 没出什么事  - 没出什么事？
- Nothing happened  - Nothing happened?
你看到他们逮捕了谁吗
Did you see who they arrested?
一个流氓 可能是偷了东西
A bum He probably stole something
跟我们没关系
It has nothing to do with us
他是我们的女邮递员的丈夫
That's the husband of our postmistress
你怎么觉得跟我们没关系
What makes you think it has nothing to do with us?
他们离婚了
They're divorced
这不能说明什么 真是的
That doesn't mean anything, damn it!
我很担心你
I was so afraid for you
如果这是个征兆是个警告呢
What if it's a, a sign, if it's a warning?
这不是
It isn't
镇定
Stay calm
记得汉斯死的时候
Remember, when Hans died.
你说过你活着没什么价值吗
You said your life wasn't worth a thing?
你说的对
You were right
所以我们能解脱
That's why we can be free
所以我们能无所畏惧
why we don't have to be afraid
但你活着
But your life
奥托 你活着 对我来说有价值
Otto, your life means something to me now
对我
means, means.
对我来说 意味着一切
Everything to me now
我们说过我们一起干的
We said we'd do this together
哦
Oh.
- 我们不会罢手  - 你不怕吗
- We won't stop  - Aren't you afraid?
今天我又停下来观察
Today I stayed again to watch
我需要看看别人看到卡片后的反应
I need to see what happens when people read it
来
Come
我的疾病证明过期了
My sick certificate had expired
所以我去看医生
That's why I went to see the doctor
否则他们会送我去集中营 拜托了
They send me to a camp otherwise. Please!
我发誓
I swear
以我孩子们的生命发誓
by the lives of my children
- 拜托了  - 两个儿子？
- Please  - Two sons?
他们都是士兵吧
And they're both soldiers, right?
两个都是
Both of them. Yes
其中一个甚至是武装党卫队的
One of them is even in the Waffen-ss
他们都还活着吧
And they're both alive, I hope?
是的 这里
Yes. Here
我的儿子卡尔 在波兰
Our Karl, in Poland
这是好消息
Well... That's good news
这人被当场抓住 有目击证人
So the man was caught red-handed. There are witnesses
而这就是罪证
And here, the Corpus Delicti
这显然是淘气鬼的字迹
It's obviously the writing of our hobgoblin
拜托 埃舍里希 我们抓到他了
Come on, Escherich We've got him
你也知道罪犯的特征 佐特
You know the criminal's profile as well as I do, Zott
罪犯是个失去独子的机械工
We're looking for a mechanic who lost his only son
你却拖来了这个可笑的家伙
And then you drag in this ridiculous character
一个赌徒
a gambler
而他甚至不住在我们的目标区域附近
who doesn't even live near our target area
还有两个活着的儿子
with two children who are very much alive
你的意思是 你相信我？
Does that, does that mean you believe me?
- 是的 你可以走了  - 谢谢 谢谢
- Yes. You can go  - Thank you. Thank you
- 出去吧  - 上帝保佑你
- Get out  - God bless you
太谢谢你了
Thank you very much
你真行
Bravo
你做了什么 你放了那个陶器鬼？
You did what? You let your hobbygobby go?
是淘气鬼 上校
Hobgoblin, Standartenfuhrer
恕我直言
With due respect
你虽然是我的上级 但身为党卫队的成员
you may be my superior, but as a member of the ss
并不一定非要是刑事专家
you're not necessarily a criminalist
我是个警察 我请求你不要干涉我的调查
I'm a policeman, and I'm asking you to let me do my job
让我用我过去的经验
just as I have learned from my experience.
经验？
Experience?
你这样的人我见的多了
I know all about guys like you
自作聪明的知识分子
Intellectuals, wise guys
别弄脏我的地板
Don't mess up my floor!
把你的血咽下去
Swallow your damn blood!
起来 起来 来 起来
Up! Up, up, up, up, up! Come. Up
你以为你聪明？
You think you're clever, huh?
而我们都是党卫队的人
And we're just the guys from the ss
什么都不懂对吗
who don't have a clue, right?
说出来 我想听你说：我比你们聪明
Say it. I want to hear it I'm smarter than you guys
说
Say it!
- 说 我听不见  - 对不起
- Say it! I can't hear you  - I'm sorry
什么
Huh?
限你两天时间
You have two days.
两天之内除掉那个你放走的人
Two days to eliminate the guy you let go
现在把他赶出去
Now, get rid of that thing!
昆格尔夫人？
Frau Quangel?
你是汉斯的母亲吧
You're Hans's mother, right?
- 是的  - 我是迪特里希
- Yes  - Uh, Dietrich
我是汉斯的同学
I was one of Hans's classmates
迪特里希 对
Dietrich. Of course
你好吗
How are you?
我很好 谢谢你 我还活着
Fine. Thank you Well, I'm alive
很高兴你从战场回来了
I'm glad you've come back
- 内克尔先生  - 对不起 我得走了
- Herr Necker?  - Excuse me, I have to go
昆格尔夫人 我…
You know, Frau Quangel, I.
我很怀念汉斯
I miss Hans a lot
我和恩诺已经没什么关系了
I have nothing to do with Enno anymore
他已经很久不是我丈夫了
He hasn't been my husband for a long time
上帝作证
before god
现在
Now.
谈到哪儿了 对了
Where were we? Yes
你正要告诉我
You were about to tell me
去哪儿能找到你的前夫
how to find that ex-husband of yours
你一直都藏在这里？
So here you've been hiding?
我知道你跟卡片毫无关系 恩诺
I know you've nothing to do with the cards, Enno
这是好消息 督查
Oh, that's good news, inspector...
可党卫队的人认为就是你
but the guys from the ss think it was you
现在他们说了算
And I'm afraid they're in charge now
也管着我
In charge of me, too
他们会逮捕你 会审讯你
They will arrest you, they will interrogate you
以他们的方式
in their own way
那我还不如死了
I'd rather be dead
你说的对
You're right
你还不如死了
You'd rather be dead
- 呃  - 嘘
- Uh.  - Shh.
没关系 这样更好一些
It's alright It's better this way
- 不 求你  - 该死的
- No. Please. No!  - Shit!
自杀？
Suicide?
好消息 埃舍里希
Good news, Escherich
绞索收紧了
The noose has tightened
嗯？
Hm?
没有新卡片了吧
No new cards?
暂时还没有
Not yet
没有了
No
嗯
Hm
谢谢你顶替弗里茨
Thanks for taking over for Fritz
快到了
It's getting closer
昆格尔工头机器过热了
Foreman Quangel, the machine is overheating
关掉它
Turn it off!
你怎么不干活
Don't you have anything to do?
路德维格
Ludwig
有东西给你
There's something for you
这很严重
It's quite something
最好交给管理层
Better take it to the management
你是个党代表
You're a party representative
你必须这么做按规矩办事
You have to do it Stick by the rules
喂
Yes, sir
今天上班的所有人
Everyone on today's shift
- 姓名地址  - 好的
- Their names, addresses  - Of course
此人肯定住在克利斯堡
Our man must live somewhere between christburger
霍德维克斯特和加布隆斯基特之间的附近
chodowieckistr and jablonskistr
没人住在那个地址 督查
No, nobody with that address, inspector
工头是谁 谁对工人最了解
Who is the foreman? Who knows his men best?
- 是弗里茨·肯帕  - 马上叫他来
- Well, that's Fritz Kemper  - Well, get him here at once
这不可能他 今早伤到自己了
That's impossible He injured himself this morning
- 谁顶替他的  - 是昆格尔
- And who replaced him?  - It's Quangel
另一个班次的奥托·昆格尔
Otto Quangel from the other shift
他的名字不在名单上
Well, his name is not in the list
你不是说所有的人吗
I, I thought it was complete
对不起 他今天只是来帮忙
Sorry. Uh, he's just helping out today
当然 他不了解这些工人
Of course, he does not know the people
他住在哪儿
Where does he live?
奥托·昆格尔
Otto Quangel
沃尔特 奥托在哪儿
Walter, where is Otto?
早上好 昆格尔工头
Good morning, foreman Quangel
早上好
Good morning
请坐
Please, have a seat
昆格尔夫人
Frau Quangel!
我们知道你在家
We know you are here!
开门
Open the door!
看看这个 昆格尔
Look at this Quangel
你肯定会对此感兴趣
This will surely interest you
你觉得这是什么
What do you think that is?
别装蒜了 昆格尔
Don't even make the effort, Quangel
总共是两百六十七张卡片
There are exactly 267 cards
你是在数有多少吗
Is that the number you were looking for?
想想吧 昆格尔
Think about it, Quangel
每张卡片都是别人上交的
Every single card was voluntarily turned into us
主动上交
voluntarily
我们自己没找到一张
We didn't find any ourselves
他们都迫不及待的上交给我们
They couldn't wait to hand them over to us
这些人都是
all those people
有的人被捕了 有一个自杀了
Some were arrested, one committed suicide
你凭什么相信
How could you seriously believe
你能改变什么
that you would change anything
昆格尔工头
you, foreman Quangel?
- 谁自杀了  - 这不重要
- Who killed himself?  - It doesn't matter
一个小人物无关紧要
A small fish. Insignificant
每个人都重要
Everyone is significant
- 这是我的错  - 这就对了
- It's my fault  - Oh, there we go
现在你认罪了
Now you have admitted your crime
你准确的告诉我 昆格尔
Tell me, Quangel, precisely
你写了多少卡片
How many cards did you write yourself
总共多少
I mean, altogether?
两百八十五张
Two hundred and eighty five
十八张
Eighteen
只有十八张卡片没被上交
Eighteen cards weren't turned in
另外我们抓到了安娜
By the way, we have Anna
那就放了她 这跟她没关系
Then let her go She has nothing to do with it
我知道你在撒谎 昆格尔
I know you are lying, Quangel
卡片内容是你老婆口述的
Your wife dictated what to write
看我像是那种
Do I look like someone who would let his wife
听老婆口述的人吗
dictate things to him?
一直都是我的主意
It was my idea from the beginning
都是我设计的 我自己携带出去
I thought it all up I carried it out by myself
她认罪了
She confessed
这是你撒谎了
Now you're lying
她认罪了 她不希望你独占功劳
She confessed. She didn't want you to get all the credit
我会签字认罪
I'll sign my confession
不过 督查 安娜
but, inspector, Anna
请不要牵连
please, don't
没这个必要
It's, it's not necessary
派个记录员到我办公室来
Send a recording clerk to my office
- 打扰一下长官  - 怎么了
- Excuse me, sir  - Yes
啊 埃舍里希
Ah, Escherich
为淘气鬼干杯
To the hobgoblin!
昆格尔
Quangel
- 安娜  - 奥托
- Anna  - Otto
- 你知道会发生什么吧  - 是的
- You know what will happen?  - Yes
是改变不了的
It can't be changed
我知道 奥托
I know, Otto
这无所谓
It doesn't matter
是的
No
全体起立
All rise!
- 希特勒万岁  - 希特勒万岁
- Heil Hitler  - Heil Hitler
时间到
Time's up
别怕 我的孩子
Don't be afraid, my child
别怕
Don't be afraid
弗洛姆法官 你能陪我一下吗
Judge Fromm, would you stay with me a moment?
我会闭上眼睛假装是奥拓
I'll close my eyes and pretend it is Otto
时间到 昆格尔
Time, Quangel
穿上
Put these on
我能为你做什么吗
Can I do something for you?
你需要什么吗
Is there something you need?
卡片和一支笔
The card and a pen
你还是把她抓走了
You took her anyway
我看过你所有的卡片淘气鬼
I read all your cards, hobgoblin
你和你老婆的
Yours and your wife's
我是唯一全部看过的人
I am the only person who read all of them.
全部除了十八张
All of them, except for 18
十八张卡片
Eighteen cards
谨以此片纪念在1940-1943年间
因制作、散发反纳粹政权卡片而被处决的韩培尔夫妇
译者｜佚名　　校润｜小众电影@电灯泡
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者